<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Assise of bread and ale, and dyuers other thynges as appereth on the other syde of the leafe.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1532</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22221</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 863.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S133</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">21533508</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 21533508</idno>
            <idno type="VID">24752</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22221)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 24752)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1739:63)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Assise of bread and ale, and dyuers other thynges as appereth on the other syde of the leafe.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprynted at London in Fletestrete in the house of Thomas Berthelet, nere the Lundite, at the signe of Lucrece,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1532?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bread --  Great Britain --  Weights and measures.</term>
               <term>Weights and measures --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:24752:1"/>
            <p>¶ The aſſiſe of bread and ale, and dyuers other thynges, as appereth on the other ſyde of the leafe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:24752:2"/>
            <head>¶ The contentes of this boke beſyde the aſſiſe of breadde and ale.</head>
            <p>¶ Fyrſte of forſtallers and forſtallynge.</p>
            <p>¶ Of regratours and regratynge.</p>
            <p>¶ Of vitayles and vitaylours.</p>
            <p>¶ Of weyghtes and meaſures. And howe moche veſſels of wyne, oyle, bonye, yeles, Salmon, and bearrynge ſhall bolde and conteyne.</p>
            <p>¶ Of pourueyours, byers, and takers of vitay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les and other thynges.</p>
            <p>¶ Of the ſtatute of wyncheſter and dyuers other ſtatutes concernynge the ſame.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:24752:2"/>
            <head>¶ The cyſe of breadde and ale.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T Was enacted / anno li. Henrici .iij. that whanne the quarter of whete is ſolde for .xij.d. than the farthynge waſtell loffe ſhall weye .vi.li.xvi.s. And the farthynge loffe Lokette of the ſame corne, and of the ſame bultell ſhal wey more than the waſtel by .ij.s. And the far<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thyng loffe cokette of corne of leſſe price, ſhall weye more than the waſtelle by .v.s. The farthyng ſym nell ſhal wey .ii.s. leſſe than the waſtelle. The far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng loſſe of clene wheate ſhal wey the coket &amp; an halfe: that is to ſay, the cokette that weyeth .v.s. more than the waſtell. The farthyng loffe of treite ſhall wey .ii. waſtelles. And the farthynge loffe of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſort of corn ſhal wey two greatter cokettes.</p>
            <p>wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the quarter of where is ſolde for .xviii.d. than</p>
            <p>the farthi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g waſtel loffe ſhal wey .iiii.li.x.s.viii.d.</p>
            <p>whan the quarter of wheate is ſolde. for .ii.s. than the farthyng waſtell loffe ſhal wey .iii.li.viii.s.</p>
            <p>whan it is ſolde for .iii.s.vi.d. than the loffe ſhal wey .liiii.s.iiii.d.ob.q.</p>
            <p>whan it is ſolde for .iii.s. than it ſhal wey .xlviii.s.</p>
            <p>whan the quarter of wheate is ſolde for .iii.s.vi.d.</p>
            <p>than it ſhall wey .xlii.s.</p>
            <p>whan it is ſolde for .iiii.s. tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſhal wey .xxxvi.s.</p>
            <p>whan it is ſolde for .iiii.s.vi.d. than the farthyng loffe ſhall weye .xxx.s.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:24752:3"/>
            <p>whan the quarter of wheate is ſolde for .v.s. than bit ſhall weye .xxviii.s.ii.d.ob.</p>
            <p>whan it is ſolde for .v.s.vi.d. than the farthynge loffe ſhall weye .xxiiii.s.viii.d.q.</p>
            <p>whan the quarter of wheate is ſolde for .vi.s. than bit ſhall weye .xxii.s.viii.d.</p>
            <p>whan bit is ſolde for .vi.s.vi.d. than the farthyng loffe ſhall weye .xix.s.xi.d.</p>
            <p>whan the quarter of wheate is ſolde for .vii.s. tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bit ſhall weye .xix.s.i.d.</p>
            <p>whan it is ſolde for .vii.s.vi.d. than the farthynge loffe ſhall weye .xviii.s.i.ob.</p>
            <p>whan it is ſolde for .viii.s. than it ſhal weye .xvii.s.</p>
            <p>whan it is ſolde for .viii.s. than it ſhal weye .xvii.s.</p>
            <p>whan the quarter of where is ſolde for .viii.s.vi.d.</p>
            <p>than bit ſhall wey .xvi.s.</p>
            <p>whan it is ſolde for .ix.s. than the farthynge loffe ſhall weye .xv.s.q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;.</p>
            <p>whan the quarter of wheate is ſolde for .ix.s.vi.d.</p>
            <p>than bit ſhall weye .xiiii.s.iiii.d.ob.q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>whan bit is ſolde for .x.s. than the farthinge loffe ſhall weye .xiii.s.vii.d.ob.</p>
            <p>whan the quarter of wheat is ſolde for .x.s.vi.d.</p>
            <p>than bit ſhall weye .xii.s.xi.d.q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>whan bit is ſolde for .xi.s. than the farthynge loffe ſhall weye .xii.s.iiii.d.q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>whan the quarter of wheat is ſolde for .xi.s.vi.d.</p>
            <p>than bit ſhall weye .xi.s.x.d.</p>
            <p>whan it is ſolde for .xii.s. than the farthinge loffe ſhall weye .xi.s.vi.d.</p>
            <p>whan the quarter of wheate is ſolde for .xii.s.vi.d.</p>
            <p>than it ſhall weye .ix.s.ix.d.ob.q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:24752:3"/>
            <p>And ye ſhall vnderſtande that the baker (as hit hath bene proued by the baker of our ſouerayne lorde the kynge) may gayne on euerye quarter of wheate .iii.d. and his branne, and .ij. loues for ſurnage, for .iiii. ſeruauntes .i.d.ob. for .ii. boyes q. for ſalte .ob. for coſto .ob. for candell. q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for wodde iii.d. for bultell ob. allowed.</p>
            <p>whan the quarter of whete is ſolde. for .iii.s. or for .iii.s.iiii.d. and barly for .xx.d. or for .ii.s. and ootes for .xviii.d. than the brewers in cities maye ſelle .ii. galons of good ale for .i.d. and in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughes .iii. gallons for .i.d. And withoute, they ought to ſelle .iiii. for .i.d. and ſo they maye welle. And wytteþ wel, that this cyſe ronneth throughe all Englande by the commaundement of our ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayne lorde the kyng. And this is the cyſe of bread and ale, accordynge as it is conteyned in the wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges of the Marſalſie of our ſouerayn lorde the kynge, after the price of the beſte wheate, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde, and thyrde ſorte. And as welle the waſtelle as other bread, of what ſorte ſo euer they be, ſhall weye after the price of meane wheate.</p>
            <p>And this cyſe of bread ought nat to be chaunged, but whan the quarter of wheate ryſeth or falleth vi.d. in the price. And euery baker ought to haue his propre marke on euery ſorte of bread. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And that no brewer reyſe nor fall a farthynge in the gallon, but whan the quarter of malte ryſeth or falleth .xii.d. in the price.</p>
            <p>And they that breake the cyſe of breadde or ale, ſhalbe amerced for the fyrſt, the ſeconde, &amp; thyrde
<pb facs="tcp:24752:4"/>tyme. And the fourthe tyme, the baker ſhall haue the iudgement of the pyllorye, and the brewer of the Tumbrelle.</p>
            <p>If there be any that by falſe meanes vſeth to ſell meale, for the fyrſte tyme be ſhall be greuouſly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſbed, the ſeconde tyme be ſhall loſe his meale, the thyrde tyme be ſhall haue the iugement of the pillory: The fourthe tyme be ſhall forſwere the towne. &amp;c. And ſo likewiſe the bakers that offend.</p>
            <p>Alſo bouchers that ſelle meſelle porke or moryn fleſſ he, for the fyrſte tyme they ſhall be greuouſlye amerced: for the ſeconde tyme ſo offendynge, they ſhal haue the iugeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the pyllory: for the third tyme they ſhalbe committed to priſon, and be ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomed: And the fourth time they ſhal forſwere the towne. And thus oughte other tranſgreſſours to be punyſſ hed: as cookes, forſtallers, and regra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of the market. whan the cookes ſithe, roſte, bake, or any otherwyſe dreſſe fyſſbe or fleſſ be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holſome for mans body.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of forſtallers &amp; forſtallynge.</head>
               <p>ANd ye ſhall vnderſtande / that a forſtaller is be, that lyethe by the waye, as vitayle or corne commeth to the markette, and byeth bit, to the intent to make the vytayle or corne derer in the markette, in burte and preiudice of the kynges people. And bit was enacted, anno .xv.E.iii. the iii. chapter, and confyrmed the .ij. yere of R. the ij. the .ij chapter, that vitayle and corne forſtalled
<pb facs="tcp:24752:4"/>ſhulde be forfayted to the kynge, and if it be ſolde, the kynge oughte to haue the value thereof, and if the offendour haue nat where with to paye, he ſhall be commytted to priſon, there to remayn the ſpace of .ii. yere or longer at the kynges pleaſure, without lettynge to baylle, or otherwyſe to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered. And if the forſtaller be atteynted at the ſute of the partye, than the partye ſhall haue the halfe of the thyng that is forſtalled and forfayted, and the kynge the other halfe.</p>
               <p>It was alſo enacted, by ſtatute of the ſtaple, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no .xxvij.E.iii.ca.xi. that no man ſhulde go by wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nor lande to forſtall wynes nor other marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſes, before they come to the ſtaple or other porte where they ſhulde be diſcharged, nor entre within the ſhyppes for that entente before the marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe were layde on lande, on peyne of their lyfe and forfayt of theyr landes to the lorde. But the peine of lyfe and forfayture of landes and tenementes was repelled, anno .xxxvij. eiuſdem regis, ca.xvi.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of regratours and regratynge.</head>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> And by cauſe I ſpake of regratours, wytteth well that a regratour is he, that byeth corne or vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle brought to the market at his owne price, and ſelleth it agayne derer in the market, in hurt of the kynges people. whiche thynge ſo regrated is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayted, and if it be ſolde the value therof is forfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp;c. Nowe bicauſe it ſo cometh to paſſe, I wyll ſpeake ſomewhat of vitayle &amp; vitaylours.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:24752:5"/>
               <head>¶ Of vitayle and vitayllours.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was defended by the ſtatute of yorke, anno .xii.Ed.ii. that no myniſter in cyte, or borowe, whiche by reaſon of his office ought to ſe the cyſe of wyne and vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle kepte, ſhulde beynge in offyce / marchaunte wynes or vytayles in groſſe or at retayle, on peyne to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayte the ſame. But oure mooſte gracious ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayne, kyng Henry the .viii. the .iii. yere of his mooſte nobull reygne, in his perlyament bolden at weſtmyſtre, the .iiii. daye of Fabruary / hath repel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led the ſame ſtatute, &amp; enacted by authorite of the ſame parlyament, for many hygh conſiderations, that whan any vytayler is choſen to beare office in any citie, towne, or borowe corporate, whiche for the tyme beinge in office, ſhuld haue the aſſiſynge &amp; correction for vitayle, that than .ij. diſcrete &amp; bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſte men of the ſame cite, towne, or borowe corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, neither of both beyng a vitayler, ſhal be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynaltie, lyke wyſe as the ſayd officer is, whiche .ij. or one, the other beynge abſent, with the ſayd officer ſhall ſet the cyſe &amp; prices of vitay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, for the tyme the ſayde vitayler ſhall abyde in his ſayde office. And after the prices and cyſes ſo ſette, it is lefull for the ſayde officers, to marchant and ſell wynes and all other vytayles in groſſe, or at retayle, withoute any forfaytinge.</p>
               <p>Alſo bit was enacted the .xxiij. yere of Edwarde
<pb facs="tcp:24752:5"/>the thyrd, the ſyxte chapter, that bouchers, fyſſ he mongers, inholders, brewers, bakers, poulters, &amp; all other ſyllers of what ſo euer vitayles, ſhulde ſylle for reaſonable price, reſpecte had to the farre or nere cariage of the ſame vitayles, and he that dothe otherwyſe, and is conuicte therof, ſhal pay the double that he receiued to the parti damaged, or in his defaut, to who that wil ſue in this behalf.</p>
               <p>And the mayres, and baillyes of cities, townes, borowghes, portis, and other places, haue power to enquere of the premiſſes, and to leuie the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde penaltie to their vſe, at whoſe ſute the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſours were conuicte. And in caſe the mayres and baylyffes be conuicte before the kynges Juſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as negligente in executynge of the premyſſes, they ſhalbe compelled by the ſame iuſtices, to pay thries the worth of the thing ſolde to hym, that is dammaged, or els in his defaute, to an other that ſueth. And yet farther, they ſhall be punyſſhed at the kynges pleaſure.</p>
               <p>It was alſo enacted, anno xxxi.E.iij.ca.x. that who that bryngeth vitayles to London, either oy lande or water, maye frely ſylle the ſame to whom be wylle, without diſtourbance of fyſſhemonger, boucher, pulter, or other. And that the mayre and aldermen ſhuld redreſſe the defautes of fyſſhmon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, bouchers, and pulters, lyke wy ſe as of them that ſylle palled wyne or ale: nat withſtandynge chartre of libertie, cuſtomes, or other pryuileges, made or vſed to the contrarye: on peyne of .M. marke for the fyrſte defaute: for the ſeconde .ij.M.
<pb facs="tcp:24752:6"/>and for the thyrde defaute to loſe theyr franchiſe.</p>
               <p>It was enacted anno .vi.R.ii.cap.ix. that vitay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lcrs in no cite nor towne through Englande ſbulde occupie the office of a iudge / except for lacke of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſufficiente: and than while be is in that office of a iuge, be nor none of his ſhall ſylle no vitayles on peyne of forfayture therof.</p>
               <p>And the .vii. yere of the ſayd kyng .R.ca.xi. the ſtatutes made the .v. and .vi. yere of his reygne, touchynge fyſſhemongers / vinteners, and other vitaylers of London, are repelled.</p>
               <p>It was alſo enacted, anno .xiii.R.ii.ca.viii. that Iuſtices of the peace in euery ſhere at theyr ceſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons holden betwene Eſter and Wichaelmas, ſhall do proclayme by theyr diſcretions, accordynge to the derthe of vitayles, what a maſon, a carpenter, a tyler, and alſo laborers / as well in Auguſte as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tymes of the yere ſhall take by the daye, with and withoute meate and drynke. And that cuerye parſone obeye this proclamation. And vitaylers to haue reaſonable gayne, after the diſcretion of the ſayde Iuſtices of peace.</p>
               <p>It is alſo ſtraytely defended, anno .vii.R.ca.xv. that no perſon, alien, denizin, nor other, cary vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayles, nor do to be conueyed, in to any parties of Scotlande out of Englande, by lande or ſee, on peyne to forfayte the ſame vitayles, or other thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of reliefe, with the ſhyppes / veſſels, cartes, or borſes that carye them, excepte the kynge gyue ſpeciall lycence to the contrarie. And be that ſpieth this, to haue the thirde parte of the forfayte. But
<pb facs="tcp:24752:6"/>Berwycke is excepted oute of this ſtatute by acte made anno .xv.R.ca.vii.</p>
               <p>It is enacted, anno i.H.iiii.ca.xvii. that the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute made, anno .vi.R.ii. howe foreyns and alyens nat beinge the kynges ennemies, bringynge fiſſhe or any other vitayles to any cyte or towne within Englande, francheſed or nat francheſed / myghte frelye ſylle the ſame by great or at retayle at theyr pleaſure / withoute any let or gayne ſayenge, ſhuld be duelye obſerued and put in execution. And alſo agayne, anno .xiiii.h.vi.ca.vi. the ſame is confyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and there vnto added / that if any diſtourbe foreyne or alyen to ſylle theyr fyſſbe contrarye to theſe ordinances, and therof is duely atteynted at the kynges or at the parties ſute, be ſhall forfayte xl.li. And be that wyll ſue for the kynge / or for him ſelfe, ſhal haue the one halfe, &amp; the king the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of weyghtes and meaſures.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is ordeined / anno .li.H.iii. that an engliſſh ſterling peny, rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de without clipinge, ſhall wey .xxxii. wheate cornes drye, taken out in the myddes of the eare: And .xx.d. make an vnce: and .xii. vnces make a li. and .viii.li. make a gallon of wyne: and .viii. ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons of wyne wake a London buſſhelle, whiche is the .viii. parte of a quarter. And the ſame yere hit was ordeyned, that the ſtanderdes, buſſbels, galo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
<pb facs="tcp:24752:7"/>and yerdes ſhulde be ſealed with the kynges yron ſcale / and ſafelye kepte on peyne of an .C.li. And that no meaſure be made in a towne, excepte bit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the meaſure of our ſouerayne lorde the kynge, and ſealedde with the common ſeale of the towneſhyppe. And if any man bye or ſyll by mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures not ſealed and examined by the meyre or bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyffes, be ſhall be greuouſlye amerced. And by the ſtatute made the .xi. yere of Henry the .vii. the .iiii. chap. all weyghtes and meaſures bothe great and ſmalle of euery cyte, borowgh, and market towne, ſhulde be dilygentlye ſene and examyned twyſe in the yere: and oftener if nede be, by the mayres, bayllies, and other beed officers.</p>
               <p>And if any man be conuicted to vſe .ii. meaſures, to bye by the more and fylle by the leſſe, be ſhall as a falſe diſceyuer, be put in pryſon, and greuouſlye punyſſhed. The ſtanderde, buſſhels, galons, and yardes / ſhall remayne in the cuſtody of the maire, or baylics, and .vi. boneſt men of the towne ſworne, before whom al meaſures ſhalbe ſealed. And that no maner grayne be ſolde by heape or cantell / ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte ootes, malte, and meale.</p>
               <p>And by the ſtatute made anno .xi.H.vii.cap.iiii. beed officers of townes maye ſygne weyghtes and meaſures with an .H. crowned: and take for the markynge of euery buſſhell .i.d. And all weyghtes and meaſures founde defectyue vpon examyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhal immediatly be bourned: and the treſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour to forfayte for the fyrſte tyme .vi.s.viii.d. the ſeconde tyme .xiii.s.iiii.d. the thyrde tyme .xx.s.
<pb facs="tcp:24752:7"/>to the mayre, bayly / or other hauynge iuriſdiction there: and for farther punyſſhement to be ſette v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the pillorye.</p>
               <p>And by the ſtatute made anno .xij.H.vii. the buſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhelle ſhall conteyne .viii. galons of wheate: and euerye galon .viii. pounde of wheate: and euerye pounde .xii. vnces, and all Troy weyghte.</p>
               <p>It was enacted, anno .xiiii.E.iii.cap.xi. that the Treaſorer of Englande ſhulde make ſtanderdes of buſſhels, gallons / &amp; weyghtes, and ſend them in to euery ſhere: and to aſſygne .ii. in euery ſhere to here / determyne, and punyſſhe ſuche as ſylle by other meaſures: and for there expenſes they ſihal haue the fourthe parte of the fynes leuied in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che caſes. And that none ſylle by buſſhell nat ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the kynges ſeale. Nat withſtandinge this acte the clerke of the market ſhall nat let to do his offyce: Nor lordes loſe theyr francheſes.</p>
               <p>The weyghte of woulle ſhal be according to the ſtanderde of the eſcheker anno .xxv.E.iii.cap.iiii.</p>
               <p>And bit is defended by ſtatute of the ſtaple made anno .xxvii.E.iii.cap.x. that none weye any mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandyſe with falſe weyghtes, on peyne to forfaite to the kynge the value of that that is ſolde, and treble damages to the partie: And Iuſtices aſſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned haue power to enquere therof as welle at the kinges as the the parties ſute: and to do execution.</p>
               <p>And anno .xxxi.E.iii.cap.ii. bit is ordeyned that certeyne balances and weyghtes of ſacke, di.ſacke. ii. and quarter / accordynge to the ſtanderde of the eſcheker ſhulde be ſente vnto all ſhereffes of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande,
<pb facs="tcp:24752:8"/>and that eche ſhulde proue theyr weygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / without any thynge gyuinge to the ſheriffe.</p>
               <p>And that none bye nor ſylle by other meaſure, on peyne to be at the kynges pleaſure.</p>
               <p>And the ſame yere the .v.chap. the weyght called Ancell was clene fordone.</p>
               <p>And the .xxxiiii. yere. the .vi.chap. it was ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that the buſſhel, pecke, gallon, pottell, quarte through all Englande within francheſes and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, ſhulde be occordynge to the kinges ſtanderde.</p>
               <p>And the .xiii. yere of .R. the .ii.cap.ix. bit was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned that one meaſure and one weyghte ſhulde be vſed through all Englande, excepte Lancaſtre ſhere, bycauſe a greatter meaſure hath alway ben vſed there than in any other parte of the realme. And be that is conuicte for vſynge falſe weyghtes or meaſures, ſhall haue balfe yeres priſonement, and gree with the partie to the double of his loſſe. And the acte made the .xv. yere of the ſame kynge R.cap.iiii. wyll that none on peyne of forfayture therof, bye more for the quarter, than .viii. buſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhels ſtriken in London or els where. And the .xvi. yere of the ſayde. R. and the xi. yere of .H. the .vi. rente ſeruyce due to lordes is excepted, which ſhall be meaſured, as it hath bene vſed. And by the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute made anno .xi.H.vii.ca.iiii. no man is preby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to bye within the ſhyppe bourde by water mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure: whiche water meaſure ſhall conteyne .v. pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes accordynge to the ſtanderde, raiſed and ſtryke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And alſo it is prouided, that the actes of weightes and meaſures ſhall nat extende nor be burtefull to
<pb facs="tcp:24752:8"/>Lornewall and Deuonſhere.</p>
               <p>It is enacted anno .i.H.v.cap.vii. and confyrmed the .xi. yere of H. the .vi.cap.viii. that all ſtatutes touchynge meaſures ſhulde fyrmelye be obſerued and kepte: and no puruciour for the kynge to bye corne but by meaſure ſtryken, and .viii. buſſhels to the quarter / and pay for the cariage of the ſame forth with. And as ofte as any purueiour or other perſon ſhall be atteynted to bye or puruey corne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wyſe, to haue a holle yeres priſonement, and paye .C.s. to the kynge, and .C.s. to the partye greued. And the mayre of London to be ſworne in the eſcheker / to execute the ſtatutes of weyghtes and meaſures. And lyke wiſe all other mayres and baylliffes to be ſworne, whan they take theyr char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges. And as well they as Iuſtices of the peace haue power to put the ſame in execution, as well at the kynges as the parties ſute.</p>
               <p>And accordynge as it is enacted anno .viii.H.vi.cap.v. that euerye cyte on peyne of .x.li euerye bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe on peyne of .C.s. and euerye village, where a conſtable is on peyne of .xl.s. ſhulde haue a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon balance, with weyghtes accordynge to the ſtanderde: and all thinbabitantes of the ſame tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes frelye to weye without any thynge gyuynge: and foreyns to paye for euery draughte of weyght xl.li.q. and for euery draught betwene .xl.li. and C.li.ob. and for euery draughte betwene .C.li. and M.li.i.d. So lyke wyſe it is ordeyned by his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente ſtatute, that vpon lyke peyne euery towne, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowghe, and village ſhall haue a common buſſhell
<pb facs="tcp:24752:9"/>ſealed accordynge to the ſtanderde, and nothynge to be taken for meaſurynge of corne. And that Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyces of peace, mayres, bayliffes, and ſtewardes of francheſes, aue power to examyn treſpaſours in the premiſſes: and them to punyſſ be vpon exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or enqueſt. But the .xi. yere of Henry the .vij. the fourth chaptre, bit was prouided that the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie conteyned in the ſtatutes for none bauyng of weyghtes and meaſures ſealed, ſhall nat extende to any towne, that is nat a citie or a market towne.</p>
               <p>It is alſo enacted the fourth yere of our moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tious ſouerayne, Henry the .viij. the .vij. chapter, that who that vſeth to bye or ſyll pewter or braſſe, and vſeth falſe beame or weyghte, ſhall forfayt .xx.s. the one halfe to the kynge, andthe other halfe to hym that wyll ſue: in whiche action protection nor effoen lyeth nat. And the partie ſhall: forfayte his beame to hym that wyll ſeyſe hit. And if the party be nat able to pay the ſome that is forfaited, than the mayres, baylyffes, or other beed officers of the place where be is fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, ſhal put hym in the ſtockes tyll the nexte market day, and than to be on the pyllorie all the market tyme.</p>
               <p>The ſtatute made anno .xvij.E.iiij.ca.iiij. wyll, that tyles ſhuld be well blanched and anuled, and the tyle erth to be dygged and caſte before the fyrſt daye of Nouembre: and that the ſame erthe be ſtyred and turned before the fyrſte daye of Febru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arye, than nexte enſuyng, and nat wrought before the fyrſt day of Marche nexte folowyng, and that therth be well tryed er bit be wrought. And euery
<pb facs="tcp:24752:9"/>playne tyle conteyneth .x. ynches and an balfe in lengthe, and .vi. and a quarter in breade, and .iij. quarters of an ynche in thyckenes. And euerye roffe or creſt tyle to conteyne in length .xiii. ynches, and .iii. quarters of an ynche in thyckenes with conuenient depenes. And euerye gutter or couerte tyle to conteyne in length .x. ynches and a halfe.</p>
               <p>And who that ſylleth any tyle nat accordynge to this ordynaunce, ſhall forfayt to the byer the dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble value, and make fyne and ranſome to the kyng, and be that wyll ſue ſhall haue ſuche proces as is vſed in action of dette at the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon lawe: in whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che action protection nor eſſoen lyeth nat. And Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyces of the peace haue power to enquere hereof. And by due infourmation to ceſſe for euerye .M. playne tyle, ſette to ſale contrary to this ordyna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce v.s. and for euery .C. roffe tyle .vi.s.viii.d. and for euery .C. corner or gutter tyle .ii.s. And the .ii. ſerchours of tyles maye preſente the defautes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Iuſtices of peace, and that preſentement is as ſtronge as of .xij. men.</p>
               <p>It is ordeyned, that .iii. barlye cornes, drye and rounde, make an ynche: and .xii. ynches make a fote: and .iii. fote make a yerde: and .v. yerdes and a balfe make a perche: and .xl. perches in lengthe and .iiii. in breade make an acre.</p>
               <p>Hit appereth in the treatiſe <hi>De compoſitione pond.</hi> that thirtye formels make a carre of leade: and ſyxe ſtone ſaue .ii. pounde make a formell: and .xii. pounde make a ſtone: and .xxv.s. in weyghte ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth one pounde. Some ſaye, that .xii. weyes after
<pb facs="tcp:24752:10"/>Troy weyght, make a carre of leade. The weye, as well of leade as of flacce, ſalte, oynions, and cheſe ſhall wey .xiiii. ſtone: and .ii weyes of wolle make a ſacke: and .x. ſackes make a laſte.</p>
               <p>And it was enacted the .xiiii. yere of E. the third, the thyrde chapter, and anno .xi.H.vii. the fourth chapter, that the ſacke of woulle ſhulde wey .xxvi. ſtone: and euery ſtone fourtene pounde.</p>
               <p>And bit was defended the .xiii. yere of R. the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde the .ix. chaptre, that no marchant nor other ſhulde bye woull by thoſe wordes, good packyng.</p>
               <p>The laſte of hearrynge conteyneth .x. thouſande / and euery thouſande .x. bundred: and euery hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſyxe tymes .xx.</p>
               <p>XX. dickers make a laſt of leather: and .x. hydes make a dycker. And .x. peyre of gloues make a dic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker. And .x. borſe ſhowes make a dycker. But .xii. peyre of gloues make a doſen: and .xij. ſkyns of parchement make a doſen.</p>
               <p>Alſo the hundred of waxe, fyſſhe, almons, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lome conteyneth .xii. ſtone and a balfe: and euery ſtone .viii. pounde, and the bundred is fyue tymes xx. and the pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de .xxv.s. And wytteth, that .xx.s. weyghte of pence maketh a pounde in confections of ſpices, as in weyeng of lectuaries: but the pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of all other thynges ſhall wey .xxv.s. Alſo in lec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuarie confections the pounde conteineth .xii. vnces and the vnce of this weight peyſeth .xx.d.</p>
               <p>The hundred of bourde, canuas, and lynnen clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the conteyneth an hundred elles and bourde: and euery hundred conteyneth .vi. tymes .xx. But the
<pb facs="tcp:24752:10"/>hundred of yron conteyneth .v. tymes .xx. and the doſen conteyneth .vi. peces.</p>
               <p>The Garbe of ſtele conteyneth .xxx. ſtone.</p>
               <p>The Seem of glaſſe is .xxiiii. ſtone: and euerye ſtone fyue pounde, and ſo the Seem conteynethe ſyxe tymes .xx. pounde.</p>
               <p>X. ſtickes make a bynde of yeles .xxv. yeles make a ſtycke. Thre and thyrty felle make a bynde.</p>
               <p>The tymber of Cony ſkyns and gryffons is .xl.</p>
               <p>The Shefe of fuſtayne is .xiii. yardes.</p>
               <p>The Shefe of ſandell is .x. yardes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howe moche veſſels of wyne / oyle, hony, yeles, ſalmon, &amp; hearringe ſhall bolde and conteyne.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſecond yere of Henri the ſyxte the .xi. chaptre it was ordeyned, that the tounne of wyne ſhulde conteyne .xii. ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes .xx. and .xii. gallons, the pype ſyxe tymes .xx. and ſyxe gallons, the tertian, and hog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſhed of Gaſcoyne wyne after the ſame rate, on peyne to forfayte the ſame wyne to the kinge.</p>
               <p>And the .xviii. yere of the ſayde kynges rayne, cap .xvii. bit was ordeyned / that tounnes, pypes, tertians, and boggeſheedes of wyne, oyle, and honye / ſhulde conteyne, the tounne .xii. tymes .xx. and .xii. gallons: the pype .vi. tymes .xx. and ſyxe gallons: the tertian .iiii. tymes .xx. and .iiii. gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons
<pb facs="tcp:24752:11"/>the boggeſheed .iij. tymes .xx. &amp; .iij. gallone. And that neyther tounne, pype, tertian, nor bog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſbeed of wyne, oyle, nor bonye be ſolde before they be gauged, on peyne to forfayt the wine, oyle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or honye ſo ſolde, or the value therof. And what countrey man ſo euer he be that ſyllethe tounne, pype, tertian, or boggeſbeed of wyne, oyle, or bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye, to any of the kynges ſubiectes for a certayne price, and lacketh of the meaſure, be ſhall rebate ſo moch to the byer as the lackynge a monteth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on pyne to ſforfaite to the king the value of all the wyne, oyle, or bony, ſolde to the contrary: nat with ſtandyng any priuey couenaunt or contracte made or to be made betwene the byer and the ſyller.</p>
               <p>The ſame is enacted / anno .i.R.iii.cap.xiii. And farther defended, that no perſon brynge in to this realme any Butte of malueſey to be ſolde, excepte it conteyne .vi. tymes .xx. and .vi. galons: Euerye barell to conteyne .xxxi. gallons and .di. And the rounlet .xviii. gallons and a halfe.</p>
               <p>And anno .iiii.R.ii.cap.i. bit is enacted, that all wynes, oyle, bonye, vinegre, and all licours ſhuld be gauged, on peyne of forfaiture.</p>
               <p>It was ordeyned anno .xxii.E.iiii.ca.ii. that no ſtrange marchant, denizin nor other, ſhulde ſylle nor put to ſale any butte of ſalmon, except it contei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned .lxxx. and .iiii. galons: the barell .xlii. galons: the balfe barell .xxi. galons well and truelye pac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, on peyne to forfayte for euery butte, barel, and halfe barell, lackinge of the ſayde meaſure .vi.s.viii.d. And that no marchaunte beynge vnder the
<pb facs="tcp:24752:11"/>kynges obeyſance, ſhulde put to ſale any veſſell of ſalmon, excepte bit were well and truelye packed, the great ſalmon by bit ſelfe withoute medlyng of grylles or broken bealed ſalmon there with. And that al grilles ſhuld be packed by them ſelfe alone on peyne to forfayte for euery butte, barel, &amp; halfe barell .vi.s.viii.d. And that no perſoné put hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge to ſale, by barell, balfe barell or fyrkyn, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte the barell conteyne .xxxij. galons, &amp; the halfe barell &amp; fyrkyn after the ſame rate / on peyne to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayte and loſe for euery barel, halfe barel, &amp; firkin, lackynge of the ſayd meaſure .iii.s.iiii.d. And that the ſame bearryng ſhulde be well &amp; truely packed, of one tyme takynge and ſaltynge. And that it be as well packed in the myddes, as at the endes, on peyne to forfayte for euery barell, halfe barell, and fyrkin ſorted, couched and packed contrary to this acte .iii.s.iiii.d. And that no marchant nor palyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſylle nor put to ſale yeles by barell / halfe ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell / or fyrkyn, excepte the barell conteyne .xlij. gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons: and the halfe barell and fyrkin after the ſame rate, on peyne to forfayte for euery barell, halfe ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rell and fyrkyn, ſo fautynge of theyr ſayd meaſure x.s. Nor to medell the galbytten, ſtoruen, pylled, nor red yeles with the good yeles: But the good to be well and iuſtely packed and ſolde by them ſelfe, on peyne to forfayte for euery barell, halfe barell &amp; fyrkin, mingled, packed, and put to ſale contrary to this acte .x.s. And that meyres, baillyffes, and other gouernours of cytes, townes, borowghes, and other places, haue power to choſe diſcrete and
<pb facs="tcp:24752:12"/>experte perſons to ſerche &amp; gauge all ſuche veſſels.</p>
               <p>The ſame acte and euery thynge therein compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is confyrmed and ratified the .xi. yere of henry the .vii.cap.xxiiii.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of purueyours.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is ordeyned among other thynges conteynedde in Magna Larts, the .xix.chap. that no conſtable of caſtell nor his bailye ſhal take any mans corn or other cataile, that dwel nat in the towne where the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell ſtandeth, excepte be paye forth with, or may haue reſpyte with good wylle of the ſyller: And if they dwelle within the ſayde towne, to paye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in fortye dayes.</p>
               <p>And bit is ordeyned the .xxi. chaptre folowinge that no lordes carte, of any perſon of holy church, of knygbte, or lady, ſhall be taken by the kynges baylies. Nor no chiefe bayllye nor other, to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mans borſes or cartes to make caryage, excepte he yelde the lyberation of olde ordeyned, that is for .ii. borſes and a carte .x. pens a day: for .iii. hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and a carte .xiiii. pens a daye.</p>
               <p>It was defended .w.i.ca.i. that none ſhuld take vitayle or carte agaynſte the owners wylle, if any dyd, to yelde double damages. And if the partye wolde nat / the kynge ſhulde haue the ſute: and the indited ſhalbe attached and diſtrayned by grande
<pb facs="tcp:24752:12"/>diſtres, that conteyneth one monethes ſpace in the kynges courte, swhere hym pleaſeth. And if they come nat at the day, they ſhall be diſtrayned by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſtreſſe conteynynge ſyxe weekes ſpace: and than if they come nat, to be atteynted, and yelde double dammages to the damaged / at the kynges ſute: and make fyne with the kyng.</p>
               <p>It is prouided. w.i.ca.xxxi. if any take vitayle, or other thynges to the kynges vſe, for garryſon or caſtell, and after they haue receyued paymente at the eſchcker, warde robe / or other place, wyl nat pay the creditours, but to theyr great damage and ſklandre of the kynge withholde their duetie / that than forthe with the duetie ſhall be leuied on their landes and goodes (if they haue anye) and paye there with the credytours, with damages / that they had therby, and to be rayned for the treſpas. If they haue no landes nor tenementes, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne in priſon at the kynges pleaſure. And bit is alſo prouyded, if any take parte of the dettes or any other lowaunce of the kynges credytours for paymente of the ſame dettes / they ſhall yelde the double, and be greuouſlye punyſſhed at the kynges pleaſure.</p>
               <p>Alſo it is prouyded if any being of the court, take moo horſes or cartes for the kynges caryage than nedeth: and taketh lowance to let them go agayn, be ſhall be greuouſlye chaſtyſed by the marſhals. And if it be done oute of the courte by any of the courte or other / be ſhal yelde treble damages, and haue .xl. dayes priſonment.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:24752:13"/>
               <p>It is ordeyned, anno .iiii.E.iii.cap.iii. that no pouruey our ſhulde make price of any thynge, nor take corne but by common meaſure ſtryken, nor take any thynge, but accordynge to the very value ſette by the conſtables or other good folkes, and paye or the kynge departe the verge. And none to haue pourueyours but the kynge, the quene, and theyr children. Nor the kynges pourueyours to take nothynge, excepte they ſhewe theyr warantye vnder the kynges greatte ſeale. And if any take oughte without warantie, and caryeth hit awaye agaynſt his wyll that oweth the ſayde goodes, to be forthe with areſted by the village where hit is, and commytted to the nexte geale: And if he be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teynted and the quantite of the thynge demaunde, to ſuffre as a felon.</p>
               <p>It was enacted anno .v.E.iii.ca.ii. that conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and .iiii. honeſte: menne of the village therto ſworne, ſhulde ſet the price of that that is puruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the kynges houſe, the quenes, and their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens. And that in the preſence of the conſtables and prayſours, tayles be made betwene the pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyours and the owners of the thynges taken, and ſealed with the pourueyours ſeales: by whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che tayles gree ſhal be made with them, of whom the pourueyunce was taken. And if any taker or purueyour for the foreſayde houſes do otherwyſe, to be forthe with arreſted by the village where hit is, and commytted to the nexte geale: And if he be atteynted therof, and the quantite of the thyng require, to ſuffre as a felon. And from henſeforthe
<pb facs="tcp:24752:13"/>the fourme and peyne conteyned in this eſtatute, to be conteyned in the commiſſyons of ſuche takers, and purueyours, whether they be vnder the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſmalle ſeale or great ſeale.</p>
               <p>It was prouided anno .xiiii.E.iii.cap.xviii. that pourueyours ſhulde take nothynge without the ſyllers agree therto. And marchauntes and other houeſt men to be deputed by the treaſorer to make purueance for the kynges warres, and for caſtelles and townes in Scotlande, Englande, and other places. And commiſſions to be ſent to the ſhereffe to make purueyance of the iſſues of his bailiwyke for the kinges horſes wher they lye at liuere. And if there be any moo founde, but a boye for euerye horſe, and an backeney for the keper, they ſhuld be put in priſon, there to remayne at the kynges plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. And to pay or they departe the verge. And lykewyſe the ſhereffes to be commanded, to make purueyaunce for the kynges dogges, of the iſſues of theyr baillywekes where they dwelle / that the countrey be nat charged with them. If any in this caſe be greued, he ſhall haue his recouerye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the ſhereffe.</p>
               <p>It was enacted anno .xiiii.E.iii.ca.i. And anno xviii.E.iii.ca.iiii.ꝓ clero, that goodes and fees of boly church ſhuld be forpriſed out of purueyours commiſſions, in what place ſo euer they be founde.</p>
               <p>It was enacted, anno .xxv.E.iii.ca.i. that pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyours commyſſyons ſhulde nat be obeyed, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte they were vnder the kynges greatte ſeale, or ſmalle ſeale, and conteyne the peyne of the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:24752:14"/>ſtatute, as is before ſayde, anno .v.E.iii. And the ſame yere .ca.vi. hit was ordeyned, that no pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyour, that purueyeth wodde and tymber for the kynges buſynes, ſhulde cutte downe the trees that grewe in or about any mans houſe, on peyne to pay treble damages to the partie greued, a yere impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, and to forgo his office.</p>
               <p>The ſame yere the .xv. chaptre it was ordeyned, that no pourueyour ſhulde take mo ſhepe before the ſherynge tyme, but as wyll reaſonably ſuffice tyll ſherynge tyme: and after ſherynge tyme to take none but ſhorne, as many as ſhall ſuffyce for the tyme to come. And he that dothe otherwyſe, and is therof atteynted at the kynges or the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſute, to be done with as a thefe or a robber. And this peyne to be conteyned in euery co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion of ſuche pourueyours.</p>
               <p>It is ordeyned the .xxviii. yere of the ſame kyng E.ca.xii. that purueyours ſhulde paye forth with for purueyance taken vnder the ſome of .xx.s. and for purueyances made to the value of .xx.s. and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue / to paye within a quarter of a yere after the purueyance made, at a certayne daye and place for moſte eaſe and trauayle of the people.</p>
               <p>The acte made anno .xxxiiii.E.iii.ca.iii. wylleth, that purueyours for pultry, and other ſmall thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſhulde paye in hande, and for great purueyan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces within a moneth or .vi. wekes after.</p>
               <p>It is ordeyned anno .xxxvi.E.iii.ca.ii. that onely the kynge and the quene ſhall haue takers, and to pay for what vitayles as they take in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, as the
<pb facs="tcp:24752:14"/>price of the markette is: and if they can nat ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, the purueyance to be rated, by the bailiffes, conſtables, and .iiii. honeſt men: and that they take in conuenyent wyſe: and nat more than ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce the .ii. houſcholdes. And the beynous name of purueiours to be changed and called byers: and the ſame byers to be ſuffycient to anſwere to the kynge and the people: and none of them to haue a deputie: and eche commyſſyon to be ſealed with the great ſeale, and euery halfe yere reſtored in to the chancery and newe made, conteynynge all the matter and maner of theyr takynges and byenges: and no byers ſaue the kynges and the quenes to be obeyed / nor theyrs, withoute they paye as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſayde. And to take all maner grayne by mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſtryken accordynge to the ſtanderde. And for caryage therof to pay in hande, and to take no mo than ſhall ſuffice for the cariage: no byer nor taker of caryage to do contrarye on peyne of his lyfe.</p>
               <p>And in the .iii.chap. folowynge hit is defended, that no byer of vitayles, nor taker of cariage take no gyfte nor other good tourne to ſpare any man, nor charge nor greue any with ſuche takynges, byenges, and caryages, through bate, enuy, or yll wyll: on peyne to yelde treble damages, and ii. yeres empriſonement, and farther to be punyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed at the kynges pleaſure: and after forſwere the courte. And if the partie wyll nat, who ſo euer wyll ſue for the kynge ſhall haue the thyrde penye recouered for his trauayle: And yet neuer the leſſe the byer &amp; taker ſhall haue the peyne in the article
<pb facs="tcp:24752:15"/>afore ſayde. And euery byer to beclare ſeuerally in his accompte all takynges and byenges of euerye ſhere- towne, village, and perſon.</p>
               <p>And it is ordeyned the .iiii.chap. folowynge, that commyſſyons ſhulde be made and ſende downe in to euery ſhere to enquere of the ſayd byers and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers demeanour. And if hit be euidently proued, that they toke more than came to the vſe of the .ii. forſaide houſeholdes, or paide nat for all that they toke, they ſhall haue iugement of lyfe and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre. And this ordynance extendeth as well to the purueiours for the great borſes of both the forſaid houſeholdes, as to the forſayde byers and takers.</p>
               <p>And it is defended on lyke peyne the .v.chap. fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowynge, that none of the kynges or the quenes houſe, of what aſtate ſo euer he be, ſhall haue a purueyour, nor take no thynge, but with the good wyll of the ſyller / and paye therfore forthe with.</p>
               <p>And hunters, faukeners, and ſcriantes of armes and other officers perteynynge to the ſayde houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdes to haue lyke peyne, if they offende.</p>
               <p>It is ordenyed anno .i.R.n.ca.iii. that prelates and clerkes greued by purueyours, ſhall recouer treble damage by action of treſpas.</p>
               <p>It is defended the .xx. yere of .R. the .ii.ca.v. that none take horſe or beaſte of any mans withoute be haue ſufficient authorite of the kynge, if any do, to be taken and layde in priſon, there to remayne, tyll he haue agreed with the partye.</p>
               <p>It is ordeyned anno .i.H.vi.ca.ii. that all ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and ordinances, made for purueiours and nat
<pb facs="tcp:24752:15"/>repelled ſhulde be kepte and executed in all poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and euery ſheriffe of the realme of Englande, to cauſe them .iiii. tymes in the yere to be proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med through his bayllyewyke, on peyne to paye a.C.s. to the kynge for euery tyme that he fauteth. And the commaundement from the kynge to hym ſent, to delyuer to his ſucceſſoure by endenture be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>twene them made: who ſhall on lyke peyne make lyke proclamation.</p>
               <p>And alſo where it was enacted anno .ii.H.iii.ca.xiiii. that no purueyour on peyne to loſe his offyce, &amp; paye as moche to the partie greued, ſhuld take any purueyance for the kynges houſe, to the value of .xl.s. and within, excepte he payde forth with: it is ordeyned anno .ii.H.vi.ca.viii. that if any pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueyour, byer, or taker dyd other wyſe, it ſhuld be lefull for any the kynges ſubiectes to reſyſt them, &amp; in no wyſe ſuffre them to make ſuche purueyan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: &amp; the couſtables / tythyngman, &amp; chefe pledge of villages to be aſſiſtyng to the poſſeſſour or ſyller of ſuche thynges, if they be requyred therto, on peyne to yelde the value of the thynges taken, to the partie greued. And that no officer of the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, on peyne to loſe .xx.li. halfe to the kynge, and halfe to hym that wyll ſue, cauſe to arreſt, vexe, or emplede any of the kynges ſubiectes, in any of the kynges courtes, for ſuche reteininges. And Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of peace in euery ſhere haue power to enquere, here, and determyne any thynge done agaynſt this acte, as well at the kynges ſute as others, and do due puniſhement and execution, and awarde dama<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges
<pb facs="tcp:24752:16"/>ges to the partye playntife, if the defendaunt be duely conuicte: and the defendant ſhall anſwere withoute ayde of the kynge. And in ſucbe actions proces to be made as in wrytte of treſpas agaynſt the peace. And this ordynance to be expreſſed in pourueyours commyſſyons. And this ordynance amonge other ſtatutes of pourueyours, byers, &amp; takers, to be ſente downe in to euerye ſbere of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande / to be proclaymed by the ſhereſſes.</p>
               <p>It is ordeined anno .xxiii.H.vi.ca.ii. that the acte touchynge pourueyours, made anno .xxxvi.E.iii. ſbulde be duely kepte and put in execution: and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer that, that euery purueyour and byer (before they had theyr commyffyons) ſhulde be ſworne in the Chancerye: to take nothynge contrarye to the ordynances made the forſayde yere. And farther bit is ordeyned, bycauſe the poure people be nat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, nor darre nat reſiſt nor ſue at the lawe the ſayd purueyours and byers, that the priſours, the vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, and all the villages adioynyng / ſhall do their deuoirs to reſiſte the byers and purueyours, that do contrarye to the ſtatutes, and in all that they may to execute the forſayde ſtatutes agaynſte the purueyours, if they be required. And be that is greued, may choſe whether be wyll take an action of dette againſt the preyſours, the village, or vyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages, and either of them, that do nat theyr deuoir whan they are required, to reſiſte (in fourme afore ſayde) the purueiours or byers: or els agaynſt the ſayde purueyours and byers, and either of them: to recouer the value of his goodes ſo taken: and
<pb facs="tcp:24752:16"/>ouer that his coſtes &amp; damages treble. Nor that no purueyour, nor other offycer of the kynges in no maner wyſe trouble nor vexe in any of the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges courtes, any of the kynges ſubiectes, for execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng of the forſay de ordynances / on peyne to paye xx.li. to the partie greued aboue his coſtes and da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages ſuſteyned in that behalfe. And that here v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon he ſhall haue a wryt of dette. And euery iſſue triable in this actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal be tried in the ſhyre / wher the goodes were taken.</p>
               <p>And the ſergeant of the Thatery ſhal ſatisfy all damages, dettes, and executions / recouered agaynſt any purueyour or byer vnder hym, in caſe the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey our or byer be nat ſufficiente. And in this caſe the partie plaintyfe ſhall haue Scire fac. to haue execution agaynſte the ſayde ſergante. And theſe ordynaunces and ſtatutes to be ſente to Iuſtices of peace, in to euery ſhire to be proclaimed euery yere and the people enfourmed.</p>
               <p>And it is defended the .xiiii.chap. folowynge that no bier or other officer of any lorde or other eſtate, excepte the kynges and the quenes, preſume to take vitayle, corne, baye, cariage, or any other thynge of any of the kynges ſubiectes agaynſt their wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, if they do, to be arreſted by the maire, ſhireffe, bayly, conſtable, or other officer of the place where it is, and put in priſon, there to remayne withoute baylle or maynpriſe / tylle the tyme they haue yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded agayne all the ſayde vitayles, cariages, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thynges taken, or the value therof.</p>
               <p>And if the ſayde mayre, ſhireffes, bayllyes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables,
<pb facs="tcp:24752:17"/>and other officers before named do the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye, that than they ſhall forfayte .xx. ſi. the one halfe to the kyng, and the other halfe to the party, of whom ſuche thynges were taken, if he wyll ſue for hit by action of dette, in whiche ſute the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant ſhal nat wage his lawe. But in caſe the party wyll nat ſue, than who that wyll ſue for the kynge and hym ſelfe, ſhal haue the one halfe of that that is recouered. And if the defendant be duelye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicte, he ſhal yelde the treble value of that that is taken to the partie that ſueth, with double coſtis, and to make fyne and ranſome to the kynge. And in all ſuche actions and ſutes, there ſhall no prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for the defendant be allowed.</p>
               <p>It is alſo ordeyned the .xxviii. yere of Henry the ſyxte, the ſeconde chaptre, that all letters patentes or grauntes that are made or to be made vnto any perſone or perſones holdyng boſtries, brewhouſe, or houſe of retayle of vitayles; to be purueyours for terme of their lyues, ſhulde be voyde and of no value or effecte. And that no perſone or perſones; ſhulde take horſe or carte, excepte he agree with the owner therof: and be to hym delyuered by the mayre, ſhireffe, baillyſſe, or conſtable, where as ſuche takynges is. And that he or they that fynde hym or them ſelfe grened contrarye to this ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, ſhall recouer treble damages by action of treſpas at the common lawe. The kynges prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatyue and prehemynence, of and in the prentyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes alwaye ſaued.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London in edibus Tho. Bertheleti. Cum priuilegio.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:24752:17"/>
            <head>¶ Of the ſtatute of wyncheſter and dyuers other ſtatutes concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge the ſame.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or to auoyde robbynges / theftes, murthers, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaughters, hit was ordeyned by the ſtatute of wyncheſtre, the fyrſte chaptre, and in more ample wyſe, the .xxviii. yere of E. the .iii. the .xi. chaptre, that crie ſhulde be made, in all ſheres, bundredes mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kettes, fayres, and all other places, where ſolemne aſſemblynge of people ſhulde be, to the ende that none ſhulde excuſe hym through ignoraunce, that euery countreye from benſeforthe ſhulde in ſuche wyſe be kepte, that forth with after robberies and felonyes were done freſſ he ſute ſhulde be made / from towne to towne, and from cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre to countre. And alſo if nede be, enqueſtes to be taken in tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / by the ſouerayne of the towne: and after in hundredes, frauncheſes / and in ſhires, and other whyle in .ii.iii. or .iiii. ſheres, in caſe whan felonies are commytted and done, in the marches of the ſheres, ſo that the myſdoers maye be atteynted: And if the counntreys anſwere nat the bodyes of ſuch myſdoers, the peyne ſhal be ſuche, that eche countre, that is to wytte, the people dwellynge in the countre ſhall anſwere for the robberies &amp; hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes done: ſo that al the hundred, where ſuche rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berye ſhall be done, with the frauncheſes that be
<pb facs="tcp:24752:18"/>within the precincte of the ſame hundredes, ſhall anſwere for the robberie done. And if the robbery be done betwene .ii. bundredes, bothe the hundre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des to gether with the francheſes that be withinne the precincte of the ſayd hundredes ſhall anſwere therfore. And the countrey after the robberye and felonye done, ſhall haue no longer tyme than .xl. dayes: within the whiche ſpace it behoueth them to agree for the robbery, and myſdedes done, orels they muſt anſwere the bodyes of the myſdoers.</p>
            <p>And for the more ſuertie of the countre it is ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the thyrde chaptre folowynge, that the gates of great walled townes ſhulde be ſhut from ſonne goynge downe to ſonne ryſynge. And that no man in ſuburbe or foreyne parte of the towne lodge but from noone tylle the nexte daye, excepte the ooſte wyll anſwere for hym. And the baillyes of townes ſhall euery weke, or at the leaſte euery .xv. dayes enquere of ſuche perſons herbouring in ſuburbes, and foreyne boroughes, and if they fynde any her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borers that receyue ſtraungers in other maner, or ſuſpecious perſones, or and if they fynde ſuche as herbourc folkes agaynſte the peace, the bayllyes ſhall punyſſ be them. And hit is commaunded by the kynge / that in townes from benſeforthe wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſhulde be kepte as they were accuſtomed of olde tyme: that is to ſaye, from the Aſcention day tyll Michaelmas, in euery cite .vi. men at eucrye gate, in euery borough .xii. men: in euery vyllage entier .vi. men or .iiii. or leſſe as the nombre of the inhabitantes requireth: and they ſhall watche the
<pb facs="tcp:24752:18"/>towne continually all the nygbte, from ſonne go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge downe to ſonne ryſynge. And if any ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger paſſe forbye them, to arreſt hym tylle the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge: and if he be nat founde ſuſpecious to lette hym go quite: and if they fynde hym ſuſpecious forthe with to delyuer hym to the ſheriffe: and the ſhereffe without damage ſhall reſceyue and ſafely kepe hym tylle ſuche tyme that he in due maner ſhall be delyueredde. And if they wyll nat ſuffre them ſelfe to be arreſted / than to rayſe ſhoute and crye vpon them, and the watche men with all the towne and townes nere ioynnynge aboute with ſhoute and crye to pourſue them from towne to towne, tylle ſuche tyme they be taken and delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the ſhereffe, as is before ſayde. And for the arreſtyng of ſuche ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers none to be encheſoned. And the .iiii. Chaptre folowynge / hit is alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, that the byghe wayes from markette townes to market townes ſhulde from benſeforth be enlarged, there as are wodde, bedges, or dyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, ſo that there be no dytche, ſhrubbes, or buſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes within .CC. foote of eche ſyde of the hyghe way, wherby a felon, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath done a ſhrowde tourne, maye ſcape: but this eſtatute extendethe nat vnto the greatte ookes and byches: And if throughe the lorde of the ſoyles defaute (whiche wylle nat cutte and caſte downe ſuche dytches, ſhrubbes, and buſſhes (after the fourme as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſayde) robberyes are commytted and done, the lorde ſhal anſwere therfore. And there be mur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther done, the lorde ſhall be reynted at the kynges
<pb facs="tcp:24752:19"/>pleaſure. And if the lorde be nat able to cut downe the ſhrubbes, the countre ſhall helpe him to do it.</p>
            <p>And the kynge wyll that in his demayne landes and woddes, within foreſt and without, the highe wayes ſhulde be enlarged, as is before ſayde. And if hit be ſo that there be any Parke nere vnto the hyghe waye, hit behoueth, that the lorde dymy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſ he his parke vnto the largeneſſe of .CC. fote nere of the hyghe waye, as is afore ſayde, or els to make ſuche a walle / dytche, or hedge, that the miſdoers can nat paſſe nor retourne to do ſhrowde tournes.</p>
            <p>Alſo bit is commaunded, that euery man ſhall haue armoure in his houſe for the kepynge of the peace, accordynge as hit is of olde tyme limytted, that is to ſaye euerye man betwene .xv. yeres and lx. yeres, to be lymytted and ſworne to haue har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys after the quantyte of his landes and goodes, that is to wytte, a man of .xv.li. lyuelode, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge goodes to the value of .xl. marke, an haber gynne, a ſalette, a ſpeare, a ſworde, and an horſe. A man of .x.li. lyuelode, and hauynge goodes to the value of .xx. marke, an habergynne, a ſalette, a ſpeare, and a ſworde: A man of an .C.s. lyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lode, a doublette, a ſalette, a ſpeare, and a ſworde. A man of .xl.s. lyuelode, and aboue to the value of a .C.s. a ſpeare, bowe, arowes, and a ſworde.</p>
            <p>And he that hath nat to the value of .xl.s. lyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lode, ſhall be ſworne to haue faux gyſarmes, a ſworde, and other ſmalle weapons. And he that hath nat to the value of .xx. markes in goodes / a
<pb facs="tcp:24752:19"/>ſpeare, a ſworde, and other ſmalle weapons. And all other that maye haue, ſhall haue bowes and arowes. Out of the foreſte and within the foreſte bowes and pillettis. And that the ſayde armours and weapons be ſeen and viewed euery yere twyſe. And in euerye hundred and frauncheſe to choſe .ii. conſtables to make the viewe of the ſayd armours and weapons: and the forſayde counſtables ſhall preſente before the Iuſtyces aſſygned (whan they come in to the con<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre) the defautes of the armours and weapons, the ſutes of the townes, and of the wayes: And alſo they ſhall preſent ſuche as lodge ſtrangers in vplandyſſ he townes, for whom they wyll nat anſwere. And the Iuſtices aſſigned ſhall preſente in euerye parlement to the kynge the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fautes, whiche they haue founde / and the kynge ſhall ſe a remedye. And that ſhereffes and baillies within francheſes and without, great or ſmalle, whiche haue baillywicke or foreſt in fee or in other maner, take good hede from henſeforth, that they folowe the crie with the countre. And after as they be, to haue horſe and harneis for that entent. And if there be any that dothe the contrarye, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables ſhall preſente theyr defautes to the Iuſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces aſſygned, and the Iuſtices ſhall after warde preſente them to the kynge, and the kynge ſhall ſe hit remedyed as is before layde. And the kynge, for the honoure of holy churche commandeth and defendeth, that from henſeforth no feyres nor mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kettes ſhall be kepte in churcheyardes.</p>
            <p>Alſo in the tyme of the ſame kinge Edwarde the
<pb facs="tcp:24752:20"/>fyrſte, that made the ſtatute of wyncheſter the .xiii. yere of his reygne, there were articles made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teynynge the maner of inquery, whan the ſayd ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute was kepte and whan nat: and who wolde ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrue it, and who wolde nat: where, howe, and by whom robberies were done: and whether the ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryffes anſwered the bodyes of the yll doers: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the gates of cites &amp; townes were cloſed from ſonne to ſonne: whether any herbored ſtrangers in ſubburbes and foreyne partes of townes / whether the bayllyes enquered thereof: bowe the watche was kepte: bowe and where bygh wayes were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged and where nat: whether all betwene .xv. &amp; lx. yere were ſworne to kepe the pece: whether they had armours and weapons in theyr houſes after the ſtent of their landes and goodes: whether the conſtables in due maner viewed the ſayd armours or nat: and laſtely whether the ſheryffe, bayllyes, and foreſters, folowed the ſhoutte and crye accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to the foreſayde ſtatute.</p>
            <p>The ſeconde yere of .E. the .iii. the .vi. chaptre, it is enacted that the ſayde ſtatute of wyncheſtre, with all other concernynge the peace / ſhulde in all poyntes be obſerued and kept, and Iuſtices aſſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned haue power to punyſſ he ſuche as diſobey and go agaynſt the ſame ſtatute.</p>
            <p>It is alſo ordeyned the .v. yere of Henry the .iiii. that watche on the ſee cooſte ouer all the realme of Englande, ſhulde be kepte with ſuche noumbre of people, in places, fourme / and maner, as hit was wonte to be in tymes paſte / and that in this caſe
<pb facs="tcp:24752:20"/>the ſtatute of wyncheſter ſhulde be obſerued and kepte. And that in the commyſſions of the peace from henſeforth to be made, this article ſhulde be put: and the Iuſtices of the peace haue power to make inquiſitions in theyr ceffyons from tyme to tyme / and them that be found in defaut to puniſſhe after the tenure of the ſame ſtatute.</p>
            <p>Alſo hit is ordeyned and enacted the .vii. yere of the raygne of kynge Rycharde the ſeconde, the .vi. chaptre, that the ſtatute of wyncheſtre ſhulde be obſerued and kepte in all poyntes, and welle and haſtylye putte in execution at the complaynte and purſuyte of anye that felethe hym ſelfe greued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte the tenure of the ſame. And to the ende that none frome henſefourthe ſhulde excuſe hym ſelfe through ignorance, bit is accorded that euery ſheryffe of Englande, ſhall in his owne perſone do proclayme the ſame ſtatute .iiii. tymes in the yere / in euerye hundred of his bayllywyke, and by his bayllyes in euery markette, as welle within lyber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as without.</p>
            <p>And hit is enacted and ordeyned. the .xxvij. yere of the reygne of the mooſte noble kynge Edwarde the thyrde, the .xiii. chaptre, that if any marchant ſtraunger or other that is robbed on the ſee, and the ſame goodes ſo robbed come in to any parties of Englande or other the kynges landes, wyll ſue to recouer the ſayde goodes, he ſhall be reſceyued to proue the ſaid goodes to be his by his markes, carte, cokette, or els by good and loyall marchates ſtrangers or other, and vpon ſuche proffes the ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:24752:21"/>ſame goodes to be delyuered vnto the marchaunt, without makyng of other ſute at the comon lawe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Thus endeth the ſtatute of wyncheſtre, with the other concernynge the ſame ſtatute. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prynted at London in Fleteſtrete / in the houſe of Thomas Berthelet, nere the Cundite, at the ſigne of Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crece. Cum priuilegio a rege indulto.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Thomas Berthelet, featuring a dragon and a dog rampant flanking a crowned portcullis, with three flowers in the foreground (not in McKerrow)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
